Wyatt here, and on today's episode of On the Brink, I was joined by Greg Janega of KPMG.
Greg discussed the firm's extensive involvement in the industry and the work they continue
to do with companies in the space.
Without further ado, I hope you enjoy my conversation with Greg.
Matt Walsh and Nick Carter are partners at Castle Island Ventures.
All of these expressed by them or the guests on this podcast are solely their opinions
and do not reflect the opinions of Castle Island Ventures.
Guests and hosts may maintain positions in the assets discussed in this podcast.
You should not treat any opinion expressed by anyone on this podcast as a specific inducement
to make a particular investment or follow a particular strategy, but only as an expression
of their personal opinion.
This podcast is for informational purposes only.
Brought down by bad mortgage investments, Lehman, which has 25,000 employees, will be
liquidated.
The federal government loans American International Group, AIG, $85 billion.
This is a different kind of market and the Fed is asleep.
The federal government is stepping in to stabilize Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac, the two mortgage
giants that have been threatened by the housing crisis.
The Bank of England has pumped 75 billion pounds more into Britain's ailing economy
with a new round of quantitative easing.
You print a couple of trillion dollars and all of a sudden people start to worry.
So out of this worry, we have something called the Bitcoin, Bitcoin.
Greg Janega from KPMG.
Thank you for joining us on the podcast today.
Thanks for having me.
Glad to be here.
I'd love to kick off before diving in with personal background.
If you don't mind, tell us a bit more about yourself and what you're up to these days.
Well, first and foremost, I'm an avid fan and listener of On the Brink and very excited
to be with you today.
Thank you.
I have to do the disclaimer, thoughts and opinions I express with you today are my own
and not representative of KPMG's views, more broadly as a firm.
Nothing I say today should be considered financial, tax, audit, accounting or legal advice.
We did ours in the intro, so now we're even.
There you go.
We're good.
Another question in terms of how I personally became interested in crypto.
So my entire 20-year career has always been in IT technology, servers, security, networks,
data center infrastructure, et cetera.
So I've always been a techie at heart.
Then about nine years ago, I got really into personal investing and did a lot to educate
myself, read a lot of books, came across the concept of diversification and alternative
assets and somehow I stumbled upon Bitcoin.
I actually don't remember exactly where.
At first, like many others, I didn't really understand it.
So I went deep down that rabbit hole, kept asking why.
Next thing you know, I'm teaching myself about the merits of Austrian economics and like
many others who go so deep, they basically never come out of that rabbit hole and they're
hooked for life.
This was exacerbated in 2020 during DeFi summer with the magic of interacting with protocols
like Aave and Uniswap.
And eventually I made the switch to work full-time in crypto almost exactly three years ago when
I joined KPMG and their innovation function as a technical blockchain subject matter expert.
So you had a deep interest in crypto and joined KPMG on the back of that interest, to be clear.
Exactly.
And can you speak to KPMG's history of being active in the crypto space over that time
window and beyond?
Actually, as far back as 2017, KPMG became one of the first public accounting firms to
audit digital assets held by public companies.
We pioneered tools and methodologies for digital asset audits, including becoming a founding
member of the AICPA's digital assets working group.
And that went to overdrive in 2020 when a large audit client originated the Bitcoin
treasury strategy and we have served them every step of the way since then.
And that opened the floodgates.
We onboarded many clients in the crypto space in the years following that.
Funds, ETF issuers, infrastructure companies, Bitcoin miners, a major stablecoin issuer,
and some of the largest operators of Ethereum and Solana validators and many more.
You touched on a lot of interesting topics.
Obviously, the reserve strategy is topical.
In that respect, today, how are you and the firm involved in the industry?
And feel free to take that any direction that makes sense.
Obviously, you touched on a number of interesting categories.
Well, we've been quite busy.
So we work closely with regulatory and standard setting entities such as the AICPA,
FASB, the SEC, etc., where we discuss the digital asset landscape.
We became one of the first approved firms to provide attestation services to the Node
Operator Risk Standard Industry Forum.
And we were actually looking into other types of crypto industry standards engagements as well.
We've done deal advisory work for some of the largest M&A activities you've seen over the
last year in the crypto space.
We've completed risk assessment work for a major payments company launching a stablecoin,
compliance work for some of the spot ETFs.
And we recently started issuing examination reports for issued stablecoins and their
related reserves as of a few months ago.
This is on top of the fact that we continue to invest in our tools and our technology
processes, specifically our patented and proprietary chain fusion tool,
which allows us to utilize on-chain data in audit evidence.
There's a structured and managed approach that's needed when dealing with on-chain data
in audits.
And that is where our tool chain fusion comes in.
That's quite a scope.
I think a lot of people can get lost in the types of activity that everyone sees in the
scheme of crypto companies being investment and payments.
But you forget about all the other needs there.
What sorts of firms are you working with?
When it comes to C-Fi, DeFi funds, you have a lot of structures in the ecosystem.
So really all kinds of firms and sizes.
And we've done from billion dollar funds and billion dollar acquisitions all the way
down to helping small DAOs with some tax work related to their tokens.
So we've done complicated tax works and tax work involving chain mergers, token migrations,
protocol upgrades, and other types of on-chain M&A work.
At the end of the day, there are a variety of regulatory and legal needs to operate
companies and participate in certain transactions in the United States,
whether it's folks needing help with tax or audit, or they need help with their money
transmitter licenses, building out risk controls, stock reports, AML KYC programs,
applying for bank charters, IP ownership and transfer issues, or other matters.
That's interesting, especially in the scope of DAOs.
I think we've seen the playbook being written in terms of how DAOs should operate in real time.
If you're able to share what's an interesting story or engagement you've had with a DAO or
protocol.
Let's think, an interesting story with a DAO or protocol.
One fun example was actually a tax engagement we did for a few venture capital funds
when DYDX, a popular perpetuals platform, was migrating from Ethereum to Cosmos.
That could have had some pretty large tax consequences if not managed properly.
So we did some work to help that.
These migrations are going to be interesting for you guys and for everyone beyond who's involved
in those activities.
How do you view the broader stack of services for crypto firms?
I imagine that the clients that you're working with, they work with a host of other participants
in other parts of the industry.
So obviously they need financial audits.
They also need smart contract audits.
There's traditional cybersecurity.
Where do you guys see yourself sitting?
And how does your role evolve in the industry's progression?
The question.
So for one thing, I'd say when an independent public accounting firm uses the term audit,
it has a very specific definition and it doesn't always align with what the crypto
industry calls an audit in the terms of something like a smart contract audit, as you mentioned.
So we're definitely quite involved in the cybersecurity space more broadly as a firm.
Things like traditional pen testing and vulnerability assessments, governance engagements
with actually Gen. AI governance being a really hot one these days.
I'd say the closest type of engagement we do that overlaps cybersecurity and crypto
revolves maybe around private key and custody management.
Things like assessing or advising on key custody, key ceremonies.
Regarding smart contract analysis, we occasionally do those types of activities
for certain audit procedures for firms, for example, that recognize material revenue
from smart contracts.
There's also a level of smart contract analysis that is required in order for us to perform
examinations for issued stablecoins and related reserves, like I mentioned before.
That being said, we've done the risk and opportunity analysis and providing things
like external smart contract attestations.
It's a service we haven't invested into date, but maybe one day.
That's a nice segue, since it sounds like there are a lot of ways that you're acting
with the firms you work with.
How has the attitude towards auditing of crypto firms you've engaged with evolved?
Well, audits are imperative for responsible capital formation in US markets.
And these crypto firms know that they owe it to their investors and stakeholders to
provide financial statements that can be relied on and that they have internal controls
over financial reporting that operates effectively for them.
So we're in the business of providing high quality audits that comply with our professional
standards that stand the test of time.
And we perform a robust client acceptance process for all new audit clients, not just
crypto companies.
As I mentioned earlier, we're proud to provide audit services to many of the leading companies
in the industry, and we're keen to work with many more.
So our services to the crypto industry will continue to evolve as the industry evolves
and the legal and regulatory picture becomes increasingly clearer.
And maybe touch on that with a little bit more depth.
How has your firm and the crypto-facing audit industry evolved to date?
Let's say our firm has evolved because our clients' needs change over time, and as do
the regulations.
The technology gets more advanced, new chains and L2s are popping up all the time that
our clients are engaging with.
So we need to make sure that we're adapting alongside that.
Another great example is that regulation is evolving.
The Genius Act, for example, if it makes it all the way into signed law, that requires
monthly attestations by public accounting firms for dollar-pegged payment stablecoins.
And we're ahead of the game on that.
And it's because of how active we are both with listening to our clients' needs as well
as engaging with entities such as the AICPA.
And what's been the AICPA's approach towards crypto both in the past and fast forward to
today?
I'd say the AICPA deserves a ton of credit for its efforts to advance the conversation
and provide guidance on accounting and auditing matters that affect the crypto industry more
broadly.
And back in 2018, the AICPA launched the first annual blockchain and accounting symposium,
convening blockchain and digital asset subject matter experts from CPA firms, technology
companies and consulting entities.
The AICPA also established its digital assets working group in 2019 to develop accounting
and auditing guides in the digital assets area.
It's a realm that we've been involved with.
It's published a popular practice aid on accounting for and auditing of digital assets,
and they've hosted a series of webcasts.
And then on the attestation side, actually just a couple months ago, back in March, the
AICPA published the 2025 criteria for stablecoin reporting specific to asset-backed fiat-pegged
tokens, which provides a common framework for stablecoin issuers to disclose information
about outstanding stablecoins and the availability of assets backing them.
Also, the AICPA is working on developing criteria for controls supporting stablecoin operations
as well.
So they've been a lot.
They've always been very curious and very easy to work with.
Yeah, it's great to hear about the stablecoin focus.
You touched on innovation a little bit.
Do you feel that currently you and the firm are able to keep pace with the innovation
that we've seen in the space?
There's a lot happening every day, obviously.
And do you think the technologies and systems in place to analyze the range of what you
see in the market are there?
Definitely.
I would say we know what it takes to serve market leaders and continue to make significant
investments in tools, data, and human capital to serve our clients.
Our clients are always engaging in new chains, more complex transactions, DeFi.
And as a result, our processes, tools, and technologies, they're constantly expanding.
There are always going to be new chains and new fields you need to be on top of.
How has your work with crypto companies evolved in the face of regulatory shifts that we've
seen?
So one way our work evolves is when new guidance is issued.
For example, from entities such as FASB or the SEC.
So when there are new standards set, both our clients and ourselves have to stay on
top of that to verify if our clients are compliant with those new requirements.
We also monitor other regulatory shifts closely and the impact both how we think about client
acceptance as well as risk assessment and other audit procedures we perform with our
clients.
Are you seeing an uptick in crypto-related needs for your more traditional clients?
Speaking on the clients, you mentioned earlier you're seeing an incorporation of stable
coins, treasury strategies, or Bitcoin holdings.
How is that impacting what you're being asked for from your traditional clients?
Great question.
So I definitely say there's an uptick in curiosity and enthusiasm across the board.
Part of my job is to provide insights to our many audit clients, even those that are not
native to the crypto industry, about what disruptors we're seeing in technology and
the corporate finance function more broadly.
So I've been talking to CFOs, CAOs, controllers, tax directors, et cetera, for years about
the developments, implications, and benefits of blockchain technology with a big focus
on stable coins.
So one example of that, how the largest ERP platforms are incorporating stable coins,
how the world's leading payments providers are leading into stable coins, it's really
starting to click for people as an option they should consider for payments and cross
border remittances.
As you might guess, the largest amount of active interest is coming from the fintech,
asset management, and banking industries.
So there's definitely been major moves some of these entities have already made in the
space, but I expect the big unlock is going to come when there is fully legislated stable
coin and market structure laws.
Banks are very risk averse, just like us, just like public accounting firms, and many
are still waiting to see what happens with advancing legislation.
All of that being said, while we are definitely seeing a large increase in activity, I'd still
say most of our traditional clients have not meaningfully engaged in the ecosystem yet.
And as the old adage goes, we're still early.
Yeah, we're still early.
How have attitudes evolved in this respect?
Because I probably imagine that the actual strategic moves to integrating crypto workflows
don't mirror where the attitudes stand.
There's usually a lag there.
Are you seeing attitudes evolving in that respect among those traditional clients?
Or do you still see a post FTX crater of sorts?
Do people view stable coins markedly different from crypto these days, speaking of stable coins?
So I find that people don't know what they don't know.
When we schedule these sessions with our many audit clients to see what topics they want
to hear about blockchain and crypto and digital assets, it's generally not high on that list.
But when we do make our way into talking about it, it's always one of the best received topics.
And again, they just don't know what they don't know.
Regarding what you mentioned about that post FTX crater there, I'd say we're almost fully
past the post FTX at this point, where it would really put a damper on the attitude
towards blockchain for a while.
Even during that really grueling bear market, we actually continue to invest in our capabilities
because we believe in the promise and ethos of the technology along with our clients.
We didn't abandon them during all of that, and they didn't abandon us.
And growth across the board is picking up, and interest again is picking up,
especially with the regulatory changes here.
Regarding how people differentiate and conflate crypto to blockchain, to Bitcoin, to stable coins,
we still have a long ways to go, I'd say, before the masses are educated on those nuances,
but it is heading in the right direction.
That's good to hear about the subject matter interest when you guys are touching on that.
What are the blockers or potential unlocks to some of those parties that you mentioned
to launching crypto powered products or workflows?
Especially for more of the traditional companies, first they would need a real business need.
So what does crypto or blockchain solve for them?
Most eyes are on efficiencies gained through disintermediation of the transfer of assets,
and I'd say most large entities in the asset management area
are actively looking at this narrative of real world asset tokenization.
It's also hard to ignore everything that the payments giants are doing in this space
and how that could innovate on settlement and payments.
Very cool.
When it comes to these use cases, payments being a chief one,
how do you feel about permission versus public blockchains?
Yeah, I get that question a lot.
So this is definitely a Greg opinion, not necessarily a firm opinion here,
so I want to be sure to clarify that.
But I personally believe there are a lot of powerful attributes
that are inherent in blockchain technology.
But I think the most important attribute that gives these systems value is censorship resistance.
With public blockchains, the fact that all you need is an internet connection
and you have access to a global financial system with no biases and no counterparty risk,
that's a very powerful and valuable thing.
Public blockchains, I feel, are effectively public goods.
And when you talk about permission blockchains,
you're effectively removing that very key attribute of censorship resistance
right out of the gate.
And maybe that calls into question the value proposition of the system
compared to a traditional centralized system
based on your typical servers, databases, APIs, etc.
Now, that being said, there are some popular permission to blockchains
used by some of the world's largest banks and asset managers
that I would actually say are a resounding success.
And I would agree they're providing an important and valuable service.
But I think this was because a result of regulatory entities
historically calling into question if public blockchains
and still safety and soundness concerns in the banking sector,
you take that and combine with the fact that it's also really difficult and expensive
to create a new system of network service databases
to execute financial transactions across.
And the software underpinning the Ethereum blockchain,
that's tried, true, and tested for executing low settlement financial transactions.
And since that software can be effectively copied,
fit for purpose, and ran in a permissioned environment,
that might be a much easier, less complicated option
than creating a parallel and alternate financial system
that you have to get industry players to agree on.
So long story short, I think they both have a time and place
depending on the facts and circumstances.
But public blockchains are resoundingly more imperative systems.
Yeah, it's a great point. It's not easy to stand up a blockchain,
both to get it working and then to actually get the flywheel going.
I think that's a lot of why you see these token incentive methods employed.
Granted, it's potentially different scope since, like you said,
that was maybe a personal view.
But how does this impact your guy's job?
KPMG's role that permission versus public blockchain dichotomy.
Well, auditing ledgers is our thing.
Permissions are public.
They have different trade-offs and efficiencies and how we audit them.
They have slightly different processes that we might utilize,
but they're structured pretty well.
And for the public chains, we have our proprietary set of tools for that.
And even for the permission chains,
we always have a way to get and correlate that data
and their internal controls and such.
And in a similar vein, how about when it comes to permissioned
or KY seed assets on chain versus permissionlessly transferable ones?
I like where you're heading with this question.
So we're actually seeing a lot of recent innovations more broadly
in the crypto space, such as with Uniswap v4 transfer hooks
and Solana token extensions as part of the token 2022 standard.
So for those that don't know, these are effectively smart contracts
that exist on public permissionless chains that allow for KYC processes
and procedures that we'll need to comply with before something like
a transfer function or any smart contract can be called on that asset.
And I think that's a super elegant way to address KYC concerns
while still keeping that base settlement layer of a public blockchain permissionless.
And on top of this, there's also a lot of ZK or zero knowledge based proofs
that can be combined with these methods to instill more privacy
alongside those KYC controls.
So as the value of tokenization and tokenized real world assets keeps growing,
I think these advancements are really logical place to build those solutions upon.
Yeah, it's exciting to see crypto become somewhat natively compliant,
having those technologies in place to just make these transfers
more comfortable for real institutional grade users.
Are there any frequent flags that come up when specifically auditing crypto companies
or anything to highlight in that regard?
I don't know if I would necessarily characterize these as flags,
but I can think of a few issues that we think are important to work through.
So how a client is able to demonstrate existence and rights to digital assets
when they are held with a third party, particularly when the third party
does not have something like a SOC report that provides assurance over its internal controls.
That's a really important issue to work through.
Also, the clients own internal controls over financial reporting,
particularly those that address the completeness and accuracy of financial information,
related party transactions, particularly given the pseudonymous nature of many blockchains.
And of course, we always see the company that has too many spreadsheets.
I have a colleague that has said before that often the digital assets
aren't the riskiest part of the audit, but rather a client's use of spreadsheets
because of all the things that can go wrong with them without robust controls.
That makes sense. I buy it 100%.
Greg, it's been great learning about you and the firm's involvement and thoughtful directions.
In closing, I want to ask what guidance would you give to
founders just getting started building crypto businesses?
Early on, I'd say most of the focus needs to be on building something that has product market fit,
something where you're providing a product or service that others find valuable and worth
paying for. And once you have that idea, maybe a prototype, MVP, etc., then I think it's important
that companies start thinking real early about the various challenges they can run into that
could threaten their business, hinder growth, or instill too much risk. I think companies should
be sure to document everything that they can in a secure fashion, focus on things like SOC-ready
IT security, bulletproof KYC and AML processes and sanctions controls, and of course, don't
cheap out on private key control and custody. So the earlier that companies can start thinking
about these things, the easier it's going to get down the line when they become a larger
focus as they scale their business. We'll leave it there. Well, Greg,
thank you for coming on and sharing you and the firm's insights. It's been great to hear about.
Yeah, it's been a pleasure. Thanks so much for having me. I appreciate it. It's been fun.
Thanks for listening to another episode of On the Brink with Castle Island. To find out more about
Castle Island, visit castleisland.vc. To listen to all of our podcast episodes,
please go to onthebrink-podcast.com or just click on the tab in our website. Thanks for listening.